90% of people make huge mistakes when buying term insurance.
Friends, today
I guarantee that
after watching this video, you won't make any mistakes related to term insurance. All
your doubts and queries related to term insurance will be
cleared today.
In today's video, we will discuss
all the features and
benefits of term insurance, and all its
riders. We will discuss
which riders you should take according to your policy,
which riders you should avoid,
for what period of time should you
buy term insurance, what should your premium term be, and
how much amount of
term insurance you should buy. Also,
in this video, I will tell you which are the top five
best insurance companies
with whom you can buy your term insurance.
So stay with this video till the end.
Hello friends, I am Ashutosh, your
personal finance coach. Let's start the video.
Many studies have shown
that most people in India who buy
term insurance are
under-insured, meaning
their term insurance doesn't cover their financial liabilities.  The
basic concept of
term insurance is that if the earning member of the family is not there tomorrow, then all the financial goals of the insured's family are equivalent to that amount. His post-retirement expenses should also be covered in that amount. To get the right amount of term insurance,
you
can either take term insurance for 2025 times your annual income or
you can calculate your human life value, in
which after calculating all your expenses
and financial goals,
you are given term insurance for that amount in present value,
which you
can calculate through any online tool or you can consult a good
financial advisor and
calculate that human life value and
get term insurance for that amount.
As important as it is to get term insurance, it is equally important to get
term insurance for the right amount. For how many years to take term insurance,
you can
take term insurance till your retirement age
or you can take term insurance till all your
financial liabilities are over,
such as  60 65 If you are
buying term insurance in your early 20s, then you
can consider term insurance for a higher age. In such a situation, the premium difference between
65, 75 and even 85 will
not be much. But when you are buying a policy in your 30s, then
you should strictly stick to your
liabilities or till your retirement age.
If you are buying a policy in your 40s or late 40s, then
you have to
cover your immediate liabilities. In
such a situation, if you buy term insurance for 10 years, 15 years and maximum 20
years, then
it will be fine because if you
buy term insurance for a longer period, then you will have to pay a
higher premium.
We get different options for paying premium - Regular
Pay, Limited Pay and Single Pay. Regular Pay
means you pay premium
every year till the end of the tenure for which you have taken the policy.
In Limited Pay, you pay premium in just five or
10 years.
In Single Premium, you pay the entire tenor in just one
premium.  We pay a premium of Rs. 100 crore
when we are taking term insurance,
our first priority should be to get
a sufficient amount of coverage.
If we are comfortable with that sufficient coverage, we
can also go for limited pay.
Otherwise, the regular pay option is the best.
In this, our premium ticket size is
quite low. In such a situation,
we do not face any problem in paying the premium in the future also.
Almost all the plans provide the
option of return of premium,
in which if nothing happens to the policyholder in the
end, then all the
premiums are refunded. Friends, this is a
very bad option. For this, we already have to
pay extra premium on 30-35 years.
So, it is better to
take a pure term insurance without return
of premium and
we can invest the remaining portion elsewhere.
In many plans, we get the option of no-cost
insurance or special exit value, in
which the policy has a term of 35 or 40 years. So,
we can surrender our policy 5 years before the end of the tenure.  By doing this, you
can get back all the premiums you have paid. This option is
available free of cost. So, if you are
taking a long tenure policy in your early 20s or if you are taking a long tenure policy, then you get it free of cost.
However, if you
want to take no-cost insurance in your 30s or 40s, then
you should
not forcibly take a long tenure policy in order to gain special exit value.
We have to strictly stick to our retirement age
or our liabilities.
Many term insurances
also give you the option of spouse cover, in which
you can give a term insurance to your spouse in your own policy on
your eligibility.
Any term insurance has
very strict criteria for income and education. In
such a situation, if your
spouse is a homemaker and does not earn
or his/her education is not that high, then
you
can still give him/her term insurance on your eligibility. But if
your spouse is earning, then giving separate term
insurance would be better
because when  If someone
adds a spouse to their own term insurance, there are
certain conditions for spousal cover.
For example, if the spouse dies before the policyholder,
you do
n't get the spouse's benefit. If both the policyholder and
spouse die together,
you still don't get spousal cover. In such a situation,
if you
can't provide term insurance to your spouse, you can club them into your policy and
provide them with a spouse cover.
While taking term insurance, there is a huge difference between the premium of a smoker
and a non-smoker.
In such a situation, many
times, despite being a smoker, people
want to take a policy by declaring themselves as non-smokers.
Friends, smoking
significantly increases the risk to your health, which is why the
insurance company charges you an extra premium.
I would suggest that
if you are a smoker, you should pay only the premium of a smoker. Apart from this, you should
not give us any misleading information related to your education and income. Apart from this, you should not give us any misleading information related to your
health or past medical
history,
or any other condition.
We should not take term insurance by hiding it.
Talking about riders or downsides,
an
important rider that we should take while taking term insurance is the
waiver of premium, in which the insurance
company waives off our future premiums under certain special conditions.
Some insurance companies waive off the premium in case of disability, some
insurance companies waive off the premium in case of critical illness,
and some insurance companies waive off
our future premiums in both the conditions.
This is a very
good rider which we must
take with our policy. Some insurance
companies also give us the option of increasing sum insured.
What happens is that when we
take our first term insurance,
our income is also less at that time, our
liabilities are also less, and in such a situation,
we purchase a term insurance according to that time,
but in the future, when
our income increases, lifestyle improves,
family grows, then our liabilities also
increase and the requirement of term insurance
increases. In such a situation, we have to take
a second term insurance at a higher age,
and in such a situation, we have to buy a higher  Premium has to be paid.
In such a situation, the option of increasing sum assured can be
a very
beneficial option in which
our coverage increases along with our fixed earnings and liabilities
and
in most of the cases,
our coverage doubles over a period of time. So,
we can also take the option of increasing sum assured
with our policy. The next
rider is Critical Illness Rider, which
pays out sum benefit on detection of any of the company's listed diseases. Sometimes its benefits are
separate from your policy
and sometimes they are accelerated, meaning that
you are given critical illness benefits by reducing your sum assured. For example,
in ICICI Prodent iProtect Smart, even if its benefits are separate or
accelerated, I would suggest that instead of
taking this critical illness policy with term insurance, you should take it from a separate
general insurance or health insurance
company.  This health insurance
is already a product of general insurance companies,
which life insurance companies purchase in bulk.
It is quite complex.
Its terms and conditions are quite complex. The
premium has to be paid high with the insurance company.
Our premium does increase over time, but these are
comprehensive policies and their
scope of coverage is quite high. The next
rider that we see with term insurance
is the accidental death
benefit rider. If this is not inbuilt in your policy, then
I would suggest
you to avoid it. You can also get an accidental death
policy from a separate general insurance
company. Their premium is also
quite low and it also does not increase with your age.
In such a situation,
we should keep both the insurances separate. What often
happens is that
if there is no accidental death proof in the case of the death of a policyholder, then the
insurance company stops the full coverage of the policy. In
such a situation, the nominee has to
face a lot of problems. So the better
option is to
definitely take out an accidental death policy.  But if you buy it from a separate general
insurance company, those policies
are more comprehensive, and in such a situation, there will be no problem
in claiming the claims of both the policies.
We see a rider called
Terminal Illness. When a
policyholder suffers from a terminal illness,
meaning a disease in which the
policyholder's death is confirmed after four to six months, the
insurance company
pays out the coverage in advance,
so the policyholder can manage it himself. This
option is not very helpful, so
if it is inbuilt in your policy,
you can avail it. There is no
need to pay anything separately for this option. To
select the best term insurance,
I have considered five parameters:
three-year average
clean settlement ratio, three-year average
amount settlement ratio, complaint
volume, company track record, and the company's
business. Claim settlement ratio can be
quite misleading individually. Therefore, it is
important to also look at the amount settlement ratio and the
industry average claim settlement ratio.  If the claim settlement ratio is 97,
we can purchase our term insurance from any company above that. In
addition to the claim settlement ratio, it
is very important to look at the amount settlement ratio, which
tells us how many
claim centers the company has and what is the amount of those claims. It is possible
that the company
accepts all small claims, but the one or two claims it is
rejecting are large claims.
If a company's average amount
settlement ratio is above 90, then it is
considered a healthy ratio. Apart from this,
complaint volume and
how many complaints the insurance company
is receiving per 10,000 claims are important factors. If a company's complaint
volume is less than 20, then we
can consider that company. Apart from investors,
we also need to look at the company's business
and its past track record.
Term insurance is a very
long-term commitment. We have to
purchase term insurance for the next 25, 30, or 40 years. In
such a situation, we should buy term insurance from such a company.  We
would like to purchase term insurance from companies whose
past record of 15, 20, 25 years
is available and the company's business is very
good, their solvency ratio is good. They issue a lot of
policies and make a lot of
claims. It should not happen that, in the
pursuit of prices, we select only small companies
which issue very few policies
and give very few claims.
We should buy term insurance from big brands whose business is
good. Based on
all these parameters, the
companies selected include
Max Life, AIA Buzz Allianz, II
Prudential Life and
their business is also quite healthy.
I will not rank these companies 125 because these
ratios keep increasing and decreasing every year.
But you can select term insurance from any one of these five
companies for yourself. I hope
all your doubts related to term insurance would have been
cleared and you would have understood
which term insurance you should buy and
how to buy it. Still, if
you have any doubts related to term insurance,  You
can ask by commenting below, friends, if you
liked the video or found it informative then do
like the video and if you
want to see such informative videos then do
subscribe to the channel, friends, that's all
in today's video, see you
in the next video, thank you.